Guide to the Mexico Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Chronological, 1522-1915; Part II. I
  - Title: "Secretario del Gobierno del Estado de San Luis Potosí...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Documents concerning the investigation into the assassination of Governor Julian de los Reyes. A number of interrogations and witness testimonies are included. 1853 (Box 56, Folder 1155, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Resumen general de los cargos y datos...." Place: [San Luis Potosí?]. Description: Large chart containing detailed budget calculations, analyses, and notes of clarification [for an unidentified agricultural property?]. 1854 Jan 1
    See: Oversize, folder 62
  - Title: Appointment. Place: Mexico City. Description: Official appointment of Manuel María Sponda as acting president of Chiapas's court of "second instance." 1854 Jan 2
    See: Oversize, folder 67
  - Title: Letter from Antonio Lavin to the provincial engineer. Place: San Fernando. Description: Letter concerning oxen for work on the "camino antiguo de los barreales." 1854 Nov 7 (Box 56, Folder 1156, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from G. García to Tiburcio Arce. Place: Cuernavaca. Description: Personal letter written to a cousin concerning a debt. 1854 Nov 25 (Box 56, Folder 1157, Reel 17)
  - Title: Documents concerning Antonio López de Santa Anna. Places: Tacubaya and New York. Description: Correspondence consisting of letters written by Santa Anna to Alejandro José Atocha and A.D. Rock. Also included is an undated decree concerning procedures for the auction of certain properties and determination of property titles. 1854-1866, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1158, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from [Francisco?] Enciso to Ignacio Martínez. Place: Oaxaca. Description: Personal letter to the [governor of Oaxaca?] warning him of the potential for danger. The writer offered political advice on how to avoid these perils. 1855 Mar 7 (Box 56, Folder 1159, Reel 17)
  - Title: Presidential decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a presidential decree concerning the payment of a portion of the internal debt with bonds. 1855 Apr 28 (Box 56, Folder 1160, Reel 17)
  - Title: Report by the bishop of San Luis Potosí. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Report about the newly established diocese of San Luis Potosí sent to the state minister for justice, ecclesiastical affairs, and public instruction. 1855 May 24 (Box 56, Folder 1161, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Leída en la repartición de premios del colegio de San Juan de Letran...." Description: Copy of a speech delivered by Luis Ortiz at a prize distribution ceremony at the Colegio de San Juan de Letran. 1855 Nov 21 (Box 56, Folder 1162, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Colección de datos sobre el laboreo de Minas...." Place: Fresnillo. Description: Series of data concerning the exploitation of mines [at Fresnillo?] compiled by the students studying mining engineering at the Fresnillo School of Mines. 1855 (Box 56, Folder 1163, Reel 17)
  - Title: Documents concerning interest payments. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Documents concerning the interest payments Antonio Rodríguez Fernández owed San Luis Potosí's ayuntamiento. The debt was secured by a house called the Parian on the central plaza. 1855-1857 (Box 56, Folder 1164, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Croquis de la batalla de S. Isidro dada el día 8 de Marzo de 1856 pr. El Gral. Castro a las tropas del Gbno." Place: Puebla. Description: Detailed sketch of the battle of San Isidro, outside of Puebla. The diagram is based on the description of General Castro, the government commander. 1856 Mar 18 (Box 56, Folder 1165, Reel 17)
  - Title: Municipal account book. Place: Pachuca. Description: Copies of the receipts for expenses of the "partido"of Pachuca. All of the accounts were paid by the "administrator de rentas." 1856 Mar (Box 56, Folder 1166, Reel 17)
  - Title: "El Admor. y el Interventor de la Tesorería de Fondos Municipales de San Luis Potosí." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Official certification that Antonio Rodríguez Fernández was obligated to pay only the sum of pesos he had at his disposal, not his entire debt. 1856 Apr 1 (Box 56, Folder 1167, Reel 17)
  - Title: Official appointment. Place: Mexico City. Description: Official certificate appointing Nicolás de la Portilla as brigade general. 1856 Apr 14
    See: Oversize, folder 33
  - Title: Letter from the treasurer of Real del Monte to Pachuca's customs adminstrator. Place: Real del Monte. Description: Letter which discusses the payment of the "iguala" and "derecho del consumo" taxes. 1856 Dec 4 (Box 56, Folder 1168, Reel 17)
  - Title: Official promotion. Place: Trieste. Description: Official certificate of promotion naming Anton von Hermann to a higher naval rank. The promotion is signed by Ferdinand Maximilian, who later became emperor of Mexico. 1856 Dec 11
    See: Oversize, folder 34
  - Author: Viglietti, Cayetano. Title: "Descubrimiento que hace el ciudadano Cayetano Viglietti de la traición de que fué víctima la República Mexicana, durante los años del 1846#1856." Description: Anti#liberal text written by an Italian immigrant describing treason committed by Mexican citizens to aid the United States in the annexation of Mexico. The first part of the text is based on documents the author obtained in Havana during the Mexican War. The latter part discusses ties between the leaders of the revolution of Ayutla and the United States. The writer argues that the United States fomented the revolution and planned to use filibusters to take over Mexico. ca. 1856 (Box 56, Folder 1169, Reel 17)
  - Tile: Index. Place: [San Luis Potosí?]. Description: [Incomplete] index (pages 21-22) of an unidentified volume of documents. 1856-1861 (Box 56, Folder 1170, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from the government of Durango to the governor of San Luis Potosí. Place: Durango. Description: Acknowledgment of the receipt of a letter announcing the departure of the forces that had occupied San Luis Potosí. The letter also congratulates the state for reestablishing public order. 1857 Jan 23 (Box 56, Folder 1171, Reel 17)
  - Title: Cover letter. Place: [San Luis Potosí?]. Description: Cover letter asking the receiver to consider documents offered by Manuel Hernández Soto. 1857 Feb 21 (Box 56, Folder 1172, Reel 17)
  - Title: Presentation by the bishop of Michoacán. Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Document written by Michoacán's bishop to the minster of justice concerning the 1857 constitution. The text discusses a number of the constitution's articles that the bishop viewed as anti-clerical, anti-Catholic, and ungodly. 1857 Apr 8 (Box 56, Folder 1173, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from the general commandant of San Luis Potosí to the governor. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Letter concerning the dispatch of troops. 1857 Apr 29 (Box 56, Folder 1174, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Carta de seguridad." Place: Mexico City. Description: Certificate granting Oliver S. Bradley, an American citizen, safe conduct in Mexican territory. 1857 May 12
    See: Oversize, folder 35
  - Title: Documents concerning Antonio Medellín. Places: San Luis Potosí, Santiago del Río, and Tlaxcalilla. Description: Five texts addressed to the governor of San Luis Potosí concerning the removal of Friar Antonio Medellín from the parish of Santiago del Río. Included are three communications from the Franciscan order's provincial for the Zacatecas district, and a letter from Santiago del Río's ayuntamiento. 1857 Aug 10-29 (Box 56, Folder 1175, Reel 17)
  - Title: Communication from the prefecture of Guadalcazar to the state secretary of goverment. Place: Guadalcazar. Description: Communication stating that the "rurales" had been ordered to take measures to deal with a group of more than eighty bandits. 1857 Sep 3 (Box 56, Folder 1176, Reel 17)
  - Title: "El H. Congreso en sesion secreta...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Copies of two documents from the state congress concerning the movement of Francisco Alemán and his accomplices; the cost of the move; and the continued surveillance of suspicious persons. The [governor's ?] response to these texts is included. 1857 Sep 6-7 (Box 56, Folder 1177, Reel 17)
  - Title: "A S. E. el Sor. John Forsyth...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of the Mexican foreign minister's reply to a communication from the minister of the United States concerning the international border and interoceanic communications via the Isthmus of Tehuantepec. 1857 Sep 12 (Box 56, Folder 1178, Reel 17)
  - Title: Presidential decree. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a presidential decree creating the "Corporación de los antiguos patriotas," outside of the regular pension system, to pay the veterans of the wars of independence. 1857 Sep 15 (Box 56, Folder 1179, Reel 17)
  - Title: Decree and letter. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Copy of a decree from the state congress ordering the governor not to assume command of the forces fighting a revolt led by Tomas Mejía. The letter was written to the governor by the general commanding San Luis Potosí's forces concerning the aforementioned congressional decree. 1857 Dec 7-10 (Box 56, Folder 1180, Reel 17)
  - Title: Cover letter, decree, and communication. Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Cover letter and legislative decree expanding the governor's powers to preserve the state's constitutional regime in light of General Zuloaga's Plan of Tacubaya. Also included is a draft of the communication which the decree mandated be sent to other state governors and congresses. 1857 Dec 22-25 (Box 56, Folder 1181, Reel 17)
  - Title: Two letters concerning a flag. Place: [San Luis Potosí?]. Description: Two letters concerning an American flag captured by Mexican forces at the Battle of Angostura. 1857 (Box 56, Folder 1182, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Acusado este gobierno ante el soberano congreso...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Documents concerning accusations against San Luis Potosí's state government before the national congress. The charges centered on actions involving the estate of Rafael Villalobos, and a decree by the state congress concerning [land for salt works?]. 1857 (Box 56, Folder 1183, Reel 17)
  - Title: "General en jefe del ejército regenerador." Place: Mexico City. Description: Letter from General Félix Zuloaga to General José María García informing him of his interim appointment as head of the "despacho del estado mayor general del ejército." 1858 Jan 22 (Box 56, Folder 1184, Reel 17)
  - Title: Order concerning an election. Place: Toluca. Description: Order from the first brigade's commanding general for individuals to appear at the municipal palace to elect the ayuntamiento. 1858 Jan 27 (Box 56, Folder 1185, Reel 17)
  - Title: Receipt. Place: [San Luis Potosí?]. Description: Copy of a receipt, originally dated 1858 November 10, in which José Pastor acknowledges the receipt of 1855 head of livestock from the estate of Father Cirto González. 1863 Sep 23 (Box 56, Folder 1186, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from Ignacio Comonfort to L. T. Cist. Place: New York. Description: Letter from an exiled president of Mexico which provided Mr. Cist with Comonfort's autograph. 1858 Nov 16 (Box 56, Folder 1187, Reel 17)
  - Title: Documents concerning education. Place San Luis Potosí. Description: Texts concerning the resignation of members of the school inspection commission, and the members of Francisca María Veronique's examining board. 1858 (Box 56, Folder 1188, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from José María de Cobos. Description: Letter from Cobos to an unidentified person discussing the need for a personal meeting to clarify/resolve a business matter. 1859 May 19 (Box 56, Folder 1189, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Juan de Jarro." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Laudatory [eulogy?] for Juan de Jarro, delivered by Ambrosio Espinosa. 1859 Nov 14 (Box 56, Folder 1190, Reel 17)
  - Title: Two decrees by Felipe B. Berriozabal. Places: Acambaro and Valle de Santiago. Description: Copies of two decrees issued by the interim commander of the army of the center. The first decree levied a wartime tax on the state of Mexico's property owners. The second decree, issued in Guanajuato, declared that any person who sought arms, horses, or money without Berriozabal's authorization would be treated as a thief. 1859 Dec (Box 56, Folder 1191, Reel 17)
  - Title: Documents concerning Francisco Carbajal Espinosa. Place: Mexico City. Description: Documents detailing Francisco Carbajal Espinosa's employment history, military service, and financial dealings. 1859 (Box 56, Folder 1192, Reel 17)
  - Title: Documents concerning the issue of bonds. Place: Mexico City. Description: Documents concerning the issue of one million pesos of bonds at ten percent [backed by nationalized ecclesiastical properties?]. Most texts are correspondence or official papers addressed to José Ramón Malo, the official named to negotiate this matter with the archbishop of Mexico. 1859 (Box 56, Folder 1193, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Reglamento que detalla las obligaciones del ecónomo de I. Ayuntamiento...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Regulations detailing certain financial obligations the ayuntamiento had to carry out, in its role as a public trustee. 1860 Jan 27 (Box 56, Folder 1194, Reel 17)
  - Title: Letter from Santiago Vidaurri to Vicente Chico Sein. Place: Monterrey. Description: Letter to the governor of San Luis Potosí discussing the military situation faced by the supporters of Benito Juárez. The letter also seeks Sein's opinion on state sovereignty. 1860 Apr 13 (Box 56, Folder 1195, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Manifesto en que el G. Santos Degallado da cuenta...." Places: León and Guanajuato. Description: Copy of a manifesto to the Mexican people, justifying the seizure of silver shipments to fund Benito Juárez's armies, as a means to shorten the war. Included are copies of communications to Degallado from Manuel Doblado, the general who actually seized the silver shipments. A text in which Degallado assumed complete responsibility for the seizure is also included. 1860 Sep 4-12 (Box 56, Folder 1196, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Expediente formada a consecuencia de la intervención q. se me [ice?] en lo relativo al préstamo q. el V. clero hizo al supremo gobo. de la plata y alajas." Place: Mexico City. Description: Group of documents concerning an order by Miguel Miramón requiring ecclesiastical corporations and communities to "loan" the government silver and gems to help pay for the war effort. Included are a copy of an official decree from the treasury concerning the methods for silver collection, and a table showing the contributions of forty-four religious organizations. 1860 (Box 56, Folder 1197, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Situación de Toluca en el mes de." Place: Toluca. Description: Copy of a report by Agustín González to Felipe Berriozabal concerning the situation in Toluca following its takeover by "constitutional" forces loyal to Benito Juárez. 1860 (Box 56, Folder 1198, Reel 17)
  - Title: "El presidente constitutional interino de la República a la H. Ciudad de Veracruz." Place: Veracruz. Description: Copy of a proclamation by Benito Juárez thanking the citizens of Veracruz for the role they played in the fight for liberty and constitutional government. 1861 Jan 4 (Box 56, Folder 1199, Reel 17)
  - Title: Lists of payment. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed lists of the monthly payments of [pensions?] made to women under four different headings: montepío civil, tabaco, moneda, and judicial. 1861 May 16 (Box 56, Folder 1200, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Última nota del Ministro Mexicano en Francia al Gobierno del Emperador." Place: Paris. Description: Copy of a diplomatic communication from the Mexican ambassador to the French foreign minister. The text refutes many of France's claims against Mexico and denounces any attempt by France to impose a monarchy upon Mexico. 1862 Mar 7 (Box 56, Folder 1201, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Anastacio Parrodi, General de División y Gobernador del Distrito Federal, a los habitantes del mismo, sabed." Place: Mexico City. Description: Proclamation of a decree by President Juárez concerning procedures to obtain claims from religious communities and pious works. 1862 Apr 21 (Box 56, Folder 1202, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Ciudadano Gobr." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Solicitation from Guadalupe Portillo seeking permission to take the examination to become a notary. 1862 Dec 6 (Box 56, Folder 1203, Reel 17)
  - Title: "Manuel Terreros gobernador del Distrito federal a sus habitantes, sabed." Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of the publication of a decree by President Juárez ordering a tax on all vouchers, orders of payments, and other financial documents valued in excess of twenty pesos. 1862 Dec 9 (Box 56, Folder 1204, Reel 17)
  - Title: "El Gral. en jefe del ejército de Oriente previniendo la separación de las religiosas de Puebla...." Place: Puebla. Description: Order by the commander of the army of the east that the members of six religious orders immediately vacate their convents. 1862 Dec 10 (Box 56, Folder 1205, Reel 17)
  - Title: Index of expedientes. Place: [State of Mexico?]. Description: Detailed index describing a total of six hundred sixty eight dossiers held in [an unidentified archive?]. The dossiers are listed under four headings: the secretariat of relations and war; secretariat of justice; treasury secretariat; and "sección directiva." 1862 (Box 56, Folder 1206, Reel 18)
  - Title: "El Coronel Juan Caamaño solicita del gobierno se la adjudique...." Places: Tlalnepantla, Pachuca, and Mexico City. Description: Documents concerning Colonel Juan Caamaño's request that the state of Mexico give him a house in Pachuca known as "la del ensaye" in lieu of his back salary. 1862 (Box 56, Folder 1207, Reel 18)
  - Title: Documents concerning Benito Juárez. Places: Mexico City, San Luis Potosí, and Chihuahua. Description: Correspondence consisting of four letters Juárez wrote to Juan Bustamante, General Juan Álvarez, and E. Plumb. Each letter has a typescript transcription and English translation. Also included are copies of a communication Juárez sent to Matías Romero, and the official certification of Juárez's death by Mexican officials. 1862-1872 (Box 56, Folder 1208, Reel 18)
  - Title: Six decrees. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copies of the proclamation of six decrees in the federal district. Five decrees are by Benito Juárez concerning taxes; the city of Guadalupe Hidalgo; the age of majority; appointment of the governor of the federal district; and silver taxes. The last decree is from the ministry of government concerning the certification of documents by former government employees. 1863 Jan (Box 56, Folder 1209, Reel 18)
  - Title: "Pociano Arriaga, Gobernador del Distrito Federal, a sus habitantes...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copies of the proclamation of four decrees by Benito Juárez in the federal district. The decrees deal with taxation; military finances; and measures concerning the properties of traitors in government controlled zones. 1863 Feb 3-12
    See: Oversize, folder 68
  - Title: "El C. Ponciano Arriaga, Gobernador del Distrito Federal a sus habitantes...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copies of the proclamation of five decrees by Benito Juárez in the federal district. The texts deal with the means to pay taxes; a new tax on capital; nationalized church properties; and chantries. 1863 Feb (Box 56, Folder 1210, Reel 18)
  - Title: Decree by Benito Juárez. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copy of a decree recognizing the services of the defenders of Puebla. The decree granted certain honors and financial rewards to these people. 1863 May 7 (Box 56, Folder 1211, Reel 18)
  - Title: Decree by the assembly of notables. Place: Puebla. Description: Printed copy of the proclamation of the decree declaring Mexico a hereditary monarchy. The same text named Archduke Ferdinand Maximilian of Austria as emperor of Mexico. 1863 Jul 12 (Box 56, Folder 1212, Reel 18)
  - Title: Decree by the imperial regency. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copy of a decree by the regency concerning new regulations affecting newspapers, book sellers, publishers, and editors. 1863 Jul 13 (Box 56, Folder 1213, Reel 18)
  - Title: "Manuel G. Aguirre, Prefecto político de México a sus habitantes...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copy of the proclamation of a decree by the regency concerning the celebration of Mexican independence. 1863 Aug 12
    See: Oversize, folder 36
  - Title: "El C. Gefe de Hacienda de este Estado...." Place: San Luis Potosí. Description: Brief text concerning livestock belonging to the estate of Cirto González. 1863 Oct (Box 56, Folder 1214, Reel 18)
  - Title: "Conbenio que han selebrado los S.S. Lica Dn. Antonio Ortiz García y Don Juan Aranda...." Places: León and San Luis Potosí. Description: Contract for the sale of the San José de Payan hacienda by Antonio Ortiz García to Juan Aranda. 1863 Nov 7 (Box 56, Folder 1215, Reel 18)
  - Title: Communications from the archbishop to the other members of the regency. Place: Mexico City. Description: Two copies of communications from the archbishop of Mexico concerning the regency's actions regarding the laws enacted by the Juárez government to nationalize ecclesiastical properties. 1863 Nov 9-11 (Box 56, Folder 1216, Reel 18)
  - Title: "Los que suscribimos con el más profundo respecto...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Unsigned text addressed to the regency and the emperor seeking the repeal of the laws which nationalized church property. 1863 Nov 12 (Box 56, Folder 1217, Reel 18)
  - Title: "José del Villar y Bocanegra, Prefecto Político del Departmento del Valle de México...." Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed proclamation of a decree by the regency describing the uniforms to be worn by city council members, treasury employees, prefects, inspectors, and chiefs of police. 1863 Dec 29
    See: Oversize, folder 63
  - Title: Four texts from the secretariat of state and foreign affairs. Place: Mexico City. Description: Printed copies of three decrees concerning the registration of foreigners; noble titles; and the national archives. The final text is the regulations for the Imperial Archive. 1863 (Box 57, Folder 1218, Reel 18)
  - Titles: Texts from the secretariat of state for treasury and public credit. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of nine decrees and laws issued by the regency. Included is a copy of the law of "contribuciones directas." Also found are decrees concerning the export of precious metals; pulque; the number of treasury officials; taxation; and other matters. 1863 (Box 57, Folder 1219, Reel 18)
  - Author: Ramirez, Ignacio. Title: "Un artículo del Nigromonte." Description: Copy of an article written in response to an article written by Emilio Castellar. The article concerns the freedom of the Americas from Spain. ca. 1863 (Box 57, Folder 1220, Reel 18)
  - Title: Six texts from the state secratariat of justice, ecclesiastical affairs, and public instruction. Place: Mexico City. Description: Copies of six printed decrees concerning such matters as the repeal of certain laws enacted by the liberals; notaries in the capital city; lawyers of the public treasury; and the state of Mexico's legal structure. 1863-1864 (Box 57, Folder 1221, Reel 18)
  - Title: " D. V. Februarii." Place: [Mexico City?]. Description: Copy of a church text written in Latin. The appendix to this text is an oration in praise of the emperor which was to be read at high mass. 1864 Apr 28 (Box 57, Folder 1222, Reel 18)